A Guide to the Record Group Vertical Files, 1960s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Record Group Vertical Files, 1960s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
VerticalFile.005
53.69 Cubic Feet 115 boxes and 1 oversize folder
In general, vertical files at Special Collections and University Archives include newspaper clippings, photocopies, ephemera, unpublished and/or informal publications, and other papers relating to a specific subject area. Files in this collection relate to Virginia Tech and its history. Topics may include, but are not limited to, colleges and departments, student organizations, administrative offices, centers and other campus units, and athletics.
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
Newman Library staff began collecting materials for vertical files during the 1960s. Special Collections and University Archives staff add to existing files and continue to create new files as the need arises.
Accruals
Materials are and will be added regularly by Special Collections and University Archives staff.
Scope and Content
In general, vertical files at Special Collections and University Archives include newspaper clippings, photocopies, ephemera, unpublished and/or informal publications, and other papers relating to a specific subject area. Files in this collection relate to Virginia Tech and its history. Topics may include, but are not limited to, colleges and departments, student organizations, administrative offices, centers and other campus units, and athletics.
Arrangement
Vertical files in this collection are arranged by record group. Within each record group, files are arranged by subgroup.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Archival Materials
Please note: Vertical files do not include official records of the university. For more information about official records in the University Archives, consult the online guide or contact Special Collections and University Archives.
Related Vertical Files:
Blacksburg Vertical Files
Montgomery County/Christiansburg Vertical Files
Southwest Virginia Vertical Files
Biographical Vertical Files (mostly relating to Virginia Tech and/or local history)
Virginia Tech and Local History Mounted Clippings (precursor to the vertical files, with materials dating back to the 1870s)
Separated Materials
The Library Newsletter, Newman News has been separated to Rare Books.
Rights Statement for Archival Description
The guide to the Record Group Vertical Files by Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, is licensed under a CC0 (https://creativecommons.org/share-your- work/public-domain/cc0/).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Women -- History; University History; University Archives
Organizations:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College (1872-1896); Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute (1896-1944); Virginia Polytechnic Institute (1944-1970); Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (1970-)
Contents List
- Record Group 1 - Board of Visitors
  Administrative History
  The legislation that created Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College (now Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University) provided for the establishment of a board of visitors as a governing body. Consisting of both appointed and ex-officio members, the board was empowered to select the president and faculty, determine salaries, handle all matters of discipline and student life, and be responsible for all property of the College.
  Governor Gilbert C. Walker appointed the first board on March 19, 1872, the day he signed the bill creating the college, and the first meeting was held March 25 and 26 in Richmond. Board appointments are still made by the governor and subject to confirmation by the Virginia Senate. Since its inception, the board has been chaired by a Rector.
  Various changes have occurred throughout the years concerning the composition of the board, primarily relating to number and qualifications of appointees and offices to be represented ex-officio. The first board was composed of nine appointed members, with the president of the State Agricultural Society and members of the State Board of Education serving ex-officio. The next year, the makeup was changed so only the State Superintendent of Public Instruction and the president of the Agricultural Society served ex-officio. Later, the president of the Agricultural Society was eliminated as an ex-officio member, but the State Superintendent of Public Instruction remained until 1966. The president of the Board of Agriculture and Immigration (now Consumer Services) became an ex-officio member after 1902, now being the only ex-officio member serving with thirteen appointed members. Four non-voting members have been added to represent the faculty, staff, graduate students, and undergraduate students.
  Scope and Content
  May include Bylaws; Citations for Meritorious Service [see also RG 6/4/3a]; William H. Ruffner Medal [see also RG 5/6/4; RG 5/2/5a]
  - RG 1 - Board of Visitors (Information)
  - RG 1 - Board of Visitors (Publications)
  - RG 1/2 - Unofficial Minutes, Correspondence, and Supporting Materials
  - RG 1/3 - Committees of the Board
    May include Task Forces of the Board
  - RG 1/4 - Individual Members of the Board
    May include Appointments to the Board of Visitors
  - RG 1/5 - Administration and Governance Structure
  - RG 1/9 - Student Board Members
  - RG 1/11 - William Preston Society
- Record Group 2 - Office of the President
  The Office of the President was established in the founding year of the university, 1872, and is appointed by the Board of Visitors.
  Please note: Records of the presidents prior to McBryde were destroyed in a fire in 1905. Active records are housed in Records Management, and permission must be obtained from the Office of the President. Records are not transferred to the University Archives until at least 30 years after the end of the president's administration.
  - RG 2 - Office of the President (Information)
  - RG 2 - Office of the President (Publications)
  - RG 2/1 - C. L. C. Minor, 1872-1879
  - RG 2/2 - John L. Buchanan, 1880-1882
    John L. Buchanan was president March-June 1880. Col. Scott Shipp was acting president in August 1880, and Professor John Hart was acting president from September 1880 through August 1881. Buchanan once again served as president from August 1881 through January 1882.
  - RG 2/3 - Thomas N. Conrad, 1882-1886
    May include Conrad Memorial Tablet
  - RG 2/4 - L. L. Lomax, 1886-1891
  - RG 2/5 - John M. McBryde, 1891-1907
    May include Investigations
  - RG 2/6 - Paul B. Barringer, 1907-1913
  - RG 2/7 - Joseph D. Eggleston, 1913-1919
    May include "Camels" [see also RG 31/12b]
  - RG 2/8 - Julian Burruss, 1919-1945
    May include Nautical Training School; Rural Electrification Short Course; Slemp Museum
  - RG 2/9 - John R. Hutcheson, 1945-1947
    May include Agricultural Conference Board
  - RG 2/10 - Walter S. Newman, 1947-1962
  - RG 2/11 - T. Marshall Hahn, Jr., 1962-1974
    May include Committee for Excellence in Teaching [see also RG 29/3]
  - RG 2/12 - William E. Lavery, 1975-1987
    Related Materials
    See also RG 4/3.
    - RG 2/12/1b - General Memoranda
    - RG 2/12/2 - Retirees' Program
      May include "New Dimensions"
  - RG 2/13 - Paul E. Torgersen (Interim President), 1987-1988
  - RG 2/14 - James D. McComas, 1988-1994
    - RG 2/14/1 - News Articles
    - RG 2/14/2b - Other Memoranda
    - RG 2/14/3 - Inauguration
  - RG 2/15 - Paul E. Torgersen, 1994-2000
  - RG 2/16 - Charles Steger, 2000-2014
    May include April 16, 2007 (April 16th shooting)
    See also RG 40/9 for April 16, 2007 shooting.
  - RG 2/17 - Timothy Sands, 2014-present
    May include Beyond Boundaries; Beyond Boundaries Presidential Lecture series
- Record Group 3 - Office of the Vice-President [obsolete, July 1966]
  In the fall of 1945, the State Legislature authorized the Board of Visitors to create the Office of Vice-President. The office was combined with the Director of Graduate Studies [RG 22] from 1949 through 1965. A reorganization in 1966 eliminated the office of Vice-President and separated the duties into the newly-created Vice-President for Academic Affairs [RG 5] and Vice-President for Administration [RG 6].
  See also RG 4; RG 5; RG 6; RG 7; RG 8; RG 21; RG 22; RG 25; RG 29; RG 35 for other Vice Presidents.
  - RG 3/1 - Walter S. Newman, 1946-1947
    See also RG 2/10.
  - RG 3/2 - C. Clement French, 1949-1950
  - RG 3/3 - Louis A. Pardue, 1950-1963
- Record Group 4 - Office of the Executive Vice-President [obsolete, July 1, 1974]
  The position of Executive Vice-President was established in 1968 as a result of the reorganization of the University's top-level administration. The position was eliminated in 1974. However, other positions have used "Executive Vice President" as part of their titles since 1977.
  May include Task Force on Research and Extension (Report 5/25/1972)
  - RG 4 - Office of the Executive Vice-President (Information and Publications)
  - RG 4/1 - Warren W. Brandt, 1968-1969
    See also RG 5/1/1.
- Record Group 5 - Office of the Executive Vice President and Provost
  The Office of Vice-President of Academic Affairs was established in 1966, out of the Office of the Vice-President [RG 3]. The title changed to Provost by the Board of Visitors on November 5, 1976. It evolved into the Senior Vice President and Provost in 1989, then University Provost and Vice President for Academic Affairs in 2001. in 2015, it became the Executive Vice President and Provost.
  May include Office for Strategic Affairs [see also RG 5/25]; Destination Areas and Strategic Growth Areas [see also RG 5/24 and individual provosts]; ACC Academic Leaders Network
  See also RG 5/24; RG 25/22 for Creativity and Innovation Strategic Growth Area.
  - RG 5 - Office of Executive Vice President and Provost (Information)
  - RG 5 - Office of Executive Vice President and Provost (Publications)
  - RG 5/1 - Executive Vice President and Provost
    May include Faculty; Interdisciplinary Research; Statement on Tenure Review Procedures and Grievances
    - RG 5/1 - Executive Vice President and Provost (Information)
    - RG 5/1 - Executive Vice President and Provost (Publications)
    - RG 5/1a - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV)
      May include SCHEV Outstanding Faculty Award
      - RG 5/1a - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) (Information)
      - RG 5/1a - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) (Publications)
    - RG 5/1b - Faculty Rewards Project
    - RG 5/1c - Degrees Conferred
    - RG 5/1/1 - Warren W. Brandt, 1966-1968
      See also RG 4/1.
    - RG 5/1/2 - Leslie F. Malpass, 1968-1974
    - RG 5/1/3 - John D. Wilson, 1975-1982
    - RG 5/1/4 - David Roselle, 1983-1987
    - RG 5/1/5 - John Perry (Interim), 1987-1989
    - RG 5/1/6 - E. Fred Carlisle, 1989-1994
    - RG 5/1/8 - Peggy S. Meszaros, 1995-2000
    - RG 5/1/10 - Mark G. McNamee, 2001-2015
    - RG 5/1/11 - Thanassis Rikakis, 2015-2017
      May include Destination Areas [see also RG 5/24]
    - RG 5/1/12 - Cyril Clarke (interim, 2017-2018), 2017-present
      Cyril Clarke was appointed interim Executive Vice President and Provost in 2017, then selected to fill the position permanently in 2018.
  - RG 5/2 - Office of Enrollment and Degree Management
    The Office of Enrollment and Degree Management was formerly Admissions and Records. The Vice Provost for Enrollment and Degree Management was formerly the Dean of Admissions and Records.
    May include Buckley Amendment; University Student Enrollment Records System (USERS), "Data Bank"; Housing; Scheduling (classes); Transfer students; Online education; College Access Collaborative; Distance learning and distributed learning; National Transfer Student Week
    - RG 5/2 - Office of Enrollment and Degree Management (Information)
    - RG 5/2 - Office of Enrollment and Degree Management (Publications)
    - RG 5/2/1 - Director of Admissions [obsolete, 1992; see RG 5/2/5]
      The Director of Admissions merged into Division of Enrollment Services in 1992.
      - RG 5/2/1 - Director of Admissions (Information)
      - RG 5/2/1 - Director of Admissions (Publications)
    - RG 5/2/2 - Office of Registrar [obsolete, 1992; see RG 5/2/5] [items also in Oversize Box 1]
      The first Registrar was appointed in 1902. Previous to that time, student record-keeping was handled by the Secretary to the President. From 1905-1911, there was no Registrar. From 1926-1937, the duties were handled by the Assistant to the Dean of the College [RG 11]. The Registrar became a sub-unit of the Office of Admissions when it was established in 1946. The Office of Registrar merged into the Division of Enrollment Services in 1992.
      - RG 5/2/2a - Commencement, 1980-1992 (Information)
      - RG 5/2/2a - Commencement, 1980-1992 (Publications)
      - RG 5/2/2b - Commencement, through 1979
      - RG 5/2/2c - Registration and Information Guide, through 1992
    - RG 5/2/3 - Honors and Awards
      May include Man of the Year (students); Woman of the Year (students); Honors Program [see also Rg 5/6/1]; Phi Beta Kappa (Wilson Essay Prize) [see also RG 31/5/4]
      See also RG 5/2/5c; Rg 5/6/1; RG 15/6.
    - RG 5/2/4 - Governor's School
    - RG 5/2/5 - Division of Enrollment Management, 1993-present [items also in Oversize Folder 1 and Oversize Box 1]
      The Director of Admissions merged into Division of Enrollment Services in 1992. The Division of Enrollment Services was renamed the Division of Enrollment Management.
      May include Summer Academy; Office of Summer and Winter Sessions; Gateway; University Open House; Campus tours / university tours; High School Spring Break / College and Department Information Fair; Hokie Ambassadors; Incoming students and over-enrollment; Hokie Preview; Undergraduate Admissions
      - RG 5/2/5a - Commencement, 1993-present
        May include William H. Ruffner Medal [see also RG 1; RG 5/2/5a]
      - RG 5/2/5b - Registration and Information Guide, 1993-present
      - RG 5/2/5c - Scholarships and Financial Aid, 1993-present [items also in Oversize Folder 1]
        May include Stuback Memorial Scholarship; FAFSA; Virginia Tech Presidential Scholarship Initiative; Westmoreland Davis Scholarships; Work Study Program
        See also RG 7/2/1c; see individual colleges, departartments, and organizations for specific scholarships.
      - RG 5/2/5d - Student Systems Computer Services, 1993-present
  - RG 5/3 - Branch Colleges
    May include Community Colleges; Roanoke Technical Institute
  - RG 5/4 - University Calendars, Academic [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    May include University Faculty-Staff Planning Calendar; Schedule of lectures
  - RG 5/5 - Cooperative Course
    May include Courses by Newspaper Program
  - RG 5/6 - Special Programs
    - RG 5/6/1 - Honors College
      In 2016, the University Honors Program became the Honors College.
      May include McNamara Scholarship; Stamps Leadership Scholarships; Odyssey Fellowships; Calhoun Discovery Program
    - RG 5/6/2 - New Faculty Orientation
    - RG 5/6/3 - Fall Orientation [items also in Oversize Box 1]
      See also RG 8/2/7.
    - RG 5/6/4 - Founders Day
      Initiated during the Virginia Tech Centennial Celebrations in 1972, Founders Day was held annually in the Spring to celebrate the signing of the state legislative bill establishing Virginia Tech on March 19, 1872, which was designated as the university's official birthday. The ceremony included the presentation of numerous awards to undergraduate and graduate students, staff, faculty, and alumni, including the William H. Ruffner Medal, awarded since 1976 by the Board of Visitors to individuals who performed notable and distinguished service to the university. Other award presentations included the Outstanding Senior Awards, the Alumni Awards for Excellence in Research and Extension, and the Alumni Distinguished Service Awards. Many of these presentations were moved to the Spring Commencement in 2006.
      - RG 5/6/4 - Founders Day, through 1989 (Information)
      - RG 5/6/4 - Founders Day, through 1989 (Publications)
      - RG 5/6/4 - Founders Day, 1990-present (Information)
    - RG 5/6/5 - Elderhostel
    - RG 5/6/6 - African American Faculty Mentoring Program
      May include African American Fellowship All But Dissertation (ABD) Program
    - RG 5/6/7 - Women's Center at Virginia Tech [items also in Oversize Box 1]
      The Women's Center at Virginia Tech was founded in 1994. The next year, the Center began Women's Month, which combined the previous events, Women's Week [RG 15/24/1] and Women's History Month [RG 15/24/2].
      May include Red Flag Campaign; Women's History Month [see also RG 15/24/1; RG 15/24/2]; VT Women Connect
    - RG 5/6/8 - Office of Academic Enrichment Programs
      May include Center for Academic Enrichment and Excellence
  - RG 5/7 - Learning Resources Center
    The Office of Information Services, predecessor of University Relations [RG 21/3], moved to Learning Resource Center in July 1971.
    See also RG 21/3.
    - RG 5/7/1 - Film, Photography, Graphics
    - RG 5/7/2 - Instructional Development
  - RG 5/8 - Innovative Instruction and Summer Training Program for High Ability High School Students
    May include Teaching Techniques
  - RG 5/9 - Computing and Information Systems [obsolete, 2015; see RG 50]
    May include S.N.A.P. (Student News Automated Phoneline)
    - RG 5/9/5 - Internet [obsolete, 2015; see RG 50/6]
      May include Graduate theses on internet
  - RG 5/10 - Office of Assessment and Evaluation [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    The Office of Assessment and Evaluation was formerly called University Planning.
    May include Department of University Plan; Program Review; Office of Outcomes Assessment
  - RG 5/11 - Institutional Research and Effectiveness
    Institutional Research and Effectiveness was formerly Institutional Research and Planning Analysis.
  - RG 5/12 - Public Service Department (Information)
  - RG 5/12 - Public Service Department (Publications)
  - RG 5/13 - Diggs Teaching Scholarship Award and Roundtable
  - RG 5/14 - University Leadership Development Program
  - RG 5/15 - Academic Assessment Program
    May include Academic Program Review
  - RG 5/16 - University-Wide Information [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    May include University-wide rankings; University-wide awards; University-wide surveys; University-wide recognitions; University-wide publicity; Blank cards (thank you, holiday)
    See also individual departments, colleges, and offices for their specific rankings.
  - RG 5/17 - Center for the Arts and General Arts programs [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    This covers events hosted by the Center for the Arts as well as general arts programs that may not be attached to other offices. May include various arts programs; Vocal Arts and Music Festival; Anne and Elle Fife Theatre; Street and Davis Performance Hall; Ruth C. Horton Gallery; Miles C. Horton, Jr., Gallery; Sherwood Payne Quillen '71 Reception Gallery; Cube [space]; TEDxVirginiaTech; Summer Chamber Music Series; Women and Minority Artists and Scholars Lecture Series; Moss Arts Center Ambassadors; Music Day
    For building information about the Moss Arts Center, see RG 6/3/2b. See also RG 25/22.
    - RG 5/17/1 - Vocal Arts and Music Festival
  - RG 5/18 - Undergraduate Academic Affairs [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    May include Student Athlete Academic Support Services [see also RG 10/11d]; First Year Experiences; Common Book; Undergraduate Academic Integrity / Undergraduate Honor System; Pathways: General Education at Virginia Tech / Pathways to Success; Office of Undergraduate Research; Student Veterans Success / Office of Veterans Services / Austin Excellence Fund for Student Veterans; Undergraduate Advising / Academic Advising Institute (AAI); University Studies; Advising Awards; Undergraduate Education; Student Success Center; Multicultural Academic Opportunities Program [see RG 5/18/1; formerly RG 8/11/2]; XL-Student Experiential Learning Conference; Majors Fair
  - RG 5/19 - Faculty Affairs
    May include Faculty recognition; Academy of Faculty Service and Academy of Faculty Leadership; AdvanceVT; Future Faculty Development Program; Faculty writing retreat; Mentoring Program for New Faculty; University Distinguished Professorships; Recruitment Matching Grant
  - RG 5/20 - Inclusion and Diversity [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    "The position of Senior Advisor to the President and Vice Provost for Inclusion and Diversity was created in 2015, following the creation of the President's Inclusion and Diversity Executive Committee in 2014.
    Previously, a Vice President for Multicultural Affairs [RG 8/11], later renamed Vice President for Equity and Inclusion [RG 6/4/5] existed. This position was then renamed Vice President for Diversity and Inclusion."
    May include President's Inclusion and Diversity Executive Council; Off of the Vice Provost for Inclusion and Diversity; Task Force on Inclusive Excellence; InclusiveVT; #VTUnfinished; Virginia Tribal Summit; ExploreVT; Presidential Principles of Community Award; Black College Institute; Topics related to the university and inclusion/diversity; Gender@VT
    See also RG 8/2/8c.
  - RG 5/21 - National Capital Region (NCR)
    May include Northern Virginia Center administration [see also RG 22/5]; Thinkabit; National Capital Region Research Development Team; Global Forum on Urban and Regional Resilience [see also RG 14/12]; Virginia Tech Research Center - Arlington; iScholars; Northern Virginia Technology Council (NVTC)
    See also RG 22/5; colleges and departments for programs offered in the NCR.
  - RG 5/22 - Learning Systems Innovation and Effectiveness
    The Vice Provost for Learning Systems Innovation and Effectiveness was created in 2017.
    See also RG 5/24.
  - RG 5/23 - Communications
    Established September 1, 2017, the Associate Vice Provost for Communications implements an interdepartmental communications program amongst the administrative units of the Office of the Provost.
  - RG 5/24 - Destination Areas and Strategic Growth Areas
    May include Adaptive Brain and Behavior; Creativity + Innovation; Data and Decisions; Economical and Sustainable Materials; Equity and Social Disparity in the Human Condition; Global Systems Science; Integrated Security; Intelligent Infrastructure for Human Centered Communities; +Policy
    See also RG 5/1/11; RG 5/1/12.
  - RG 5/25 - Office for Strategic Affairs
    May include Strategic Planning Committees; VT Stories; Council on VT History [see also RG 32/3]
    See also RG 5.
  - RG 5/26 - Innovation Campus
    The Virginia Tech Innovation Campus in Alexandra, Virginia, was announced on November 13, 2018.
    May include Amazon in Alexandria
  - RG 5/27 - Academic Resource Management
    The Vice Provost of Academic Resource Management was formerly the Vice Provost of Resource Management and Institutional Effectiveness.
- Record Group 6 - Division of Operations
  Established in 1966, the Office of Administration later became the Division of Administrative Services, and in 2017, it became the Division of Operations.
  May include Economic Initiative Plan
  - RG 6 - Division of Operations (Information)
  - RG 6 - Division of Operations (Publications)
  - RG 6a - Senior Vice President and Chief Business Officer
    The position of Senior Vice President for Operations and Administration was established in 2017. The title was later renamed Senior Vice President and Chief Business Officer.
  - RG 6/1 - Vice President for Operations